Guide to the Edwin P. Kilroe Papers 1832-1950 (bulk, 1890s-1948) MS 3125
New-York Historical Society
Edwin P. Kilroe papers
1832-1950 (bulk, 1890s-1948)
New-York Historical Society
Kilroe, Edwin P.
MS 3125
66 Linear feet in 56 boxes of various sizes
The collection holds the papers of Edwin P. Kilroe (1882-1953) representing his academic career (especially at Columbia University); athletics (especially wrestling at Columbia); family history and connections to Wayne County, Pennsylvania; involvement with a broad range of organizations, such as the Catholic Writers Guild, New York City Democratic Party clubs (i.e., Tammany Hall), historical societies, lawyer bar associations, and others; cattle breeding at the Kilroe Farm in Tanners Falls, Pennsylvania; and work in the Office of New York County District Attorney Edward Swann from 1916-24; and more. There are a small number of documents related to Kilroe's work as an attorney for Twentieth Century-Fox Films in the 1930s-40s, but with a rich set of scripts, photographs, posters, and publicity material for four of the studio's films: "Greenwich Village," "Sweet Rosie O'Grady," "When Irish Eyes Are Smiling," and "Wilson."
Arrangement
The collection was inventoried in December 2021-January 2022 as it was removed from shelves and packed for offsite storage. Accordingly, the container list is presented as a list of contents by box. During the inventory and packing, an attempt was made to keep related materials together but this was not always possible because of the varying sizes of the content and difficulty in identifying related materials across the shelves in a compressed timeframe. Generally, bound volumes of documents appear first in the container list with accordion folders of documents later, but this was not consistently adhered to when the collection was inventoried and packed.
Biographical / Historical
Edwin Patrick Kilroe was born April 19, 1882, in Tanners Falls, Wayne County, Pennsylvania. (His birth year seems to be in some dispute. Columbia University uses 1880 for his collection there. Some newspaper accounts from the early 20th century refer to 1883. A biographical note written by Kilroe himself in 1911 in connection with his application for admission to the Pennsylvania bar refers to 1882.) Edwin's mother was Sarah Doherty Kilroe (1859-1928), who was born in County Sligo in Ireland and emigrated to the United States as an infant with her parents in 1861. Her parents settled at Tanners Falls, establishing a farm there (an online map from the time shows the family name as "Dougherty") that would remain in the family through Edwin's lifetime (it is now the site of a Himalayan Institute). Edwin's father was John Charles Kilroe (1853-1902), also an Irish immigrant. Sarah and John married in the late 1870s. They were both, apparently, Catholic, as was Edwin, who retained his connections to Catholicism and Catholic institutions throughout his life, including (to name just one example) as a member of the Catholic Writers Guild from the 1920s and an officer in the 1930s-1940s. Sarah and John had twelve children and Edwin seems to have been the eldest.
Edwin attended schools in Wayne County, graduating from Honesdale High School. In the late 1890s, Kilroe moved to Jersey City to live with his uncle while attending schools in New York, which included Packards Business College, Paine's Business College, New York Preparatory School, and Dwight School for Boys. Graduating from Dwight in 1900, he then entered Columbia College, receiving his A.B. degree in 1904. Continuing at Columbia, he earned a Masters in 1905 and his law degree in 1906. He received his Ph.D. in 1913 from Columbia for which he wrote a thesis on Tammany Hall ("Saint Tammany and the origin of the Society of Tammany, or Columbian order in the city of New York"). Kilroe was athletic, playing football in high school and wrestling (among other sports) at Columbia. Among many interests, Kilroe maintained connections throughout his life as an alumni of Columbia and its wrestling team, of which he was an organizer and coach during his student years.
Kilroe was admitted to the New York bar in 1906 and formed the partnership Kilroe & Swarts (likely Louis E. Swarts) in 1907, located at 5 Beekman Steet in New York City. During these years he became an active member of the Democratic Party, holding a seat on the New York County Committee and various offices for the Minnetonkah and Monangahela Democratic clubs. In 1911, it appears he considered relocating to Scranton, Pennsylvania, and applied for admission to that state's bar. Kilroe was eventually admitted in 1915 but he did not relocate, continuing to practice law from the Beekman Street address, though no longer in partnership with Swarts. In late 1915, he applied to Edward Swann, the New York County's Attorney General-elect, for a position, and he was hired as Deputy Assistant District Attorney. He held that position from January 1916 through 1917, when he was promoted to Assistant District Attorney.
In the D.A.'s Office, Kilroe was involved in the prosecution of many cases. Among them were investigations in 1918 into charities fraud, which would lead to hearings before the U.S. Senate, and into theatre ticket speculation. In late 1920, he faced charges of corruption for conspiring with Louis Swarts and others to decline to bring Napoleon Arthur Bourassa up on bigamy charges. Kilroe retained the support of his boss, Swann, in the matter and seems eventually to have been found not guilty of the charges. Kilroe's compiled list of cases show a gap for 1921-22, while he was on trial, but back on the job in 1923. He resigned from the District Attorney's Office in 1924, returning to private practice. At that time he assisted in the compilation of "A History of Tammany," published by the New York County Democratic Committee.
By 1929, Kilroe was hired into the legal department of Fox Film Corporation. In a 1935 merger, the company became known as Twentieth Century-Fox Film Corporation. Kilroe was briefly a director of the company in the early 1940s, but his overall role in the company seems to have been as an intellectual property rights attorney. He may have left the company in the mid-late 1940s, but remained at least an advisor to it.
In 1942, Kilroe donated over 100,000 documents he had amassed concerning Tammany to Columbia University. In 1944 and at various times afterward, he also donated much of his personal papers (the present collection) to New-York Historical Society (he was a member). Some of the documents in this collection bear Kilroe's "Tammaniana" collection label. (See box 15 for a list compiled by Kilroe of the institutions he donated material to, through 1948.) He retained his connections to the family farm and his youth in Honesdale, collecting historical materials about it, forming a Wayne County Society in New York City, and being engaged in cattle breeding. At least some of the related material is in the N-YHS collection. Edwin Kilroe died in 1953.
(The above note was based primarily on documents in the collection, and some on-line documents.)
Access Restrictions
Materials in this collection are stored offsite. For more information on making arrangements to consult them, please visit www.nyhistory.org/library/visit.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Edwin P. Kilroe in at least two accessions, 1944 and 1950. A small accession of certificates and bookplates given by Kilroe in 1940 to the Wayne County Historical Association was donated by that organization to N-YHS in August 2022 and added to this collection.
Scope and Contents
The Edwin P. Kilroe papers hold a sprawling array of scrapbooks, original correpondence, photostat copies of historical and family documents, ephemera, clippings, publications, photographs, and other materials related to the diverse career, life and interests of Kilroe. Several members of his family are also well-represented in the collection, perhaps especially his mother, Sarah Doherty Kilroe, and his brothers, who served in the military in World War I and World War II.
Edwin's student years and alumni connections, especially with Columbia College and University, are reflected in publications, school notes, photographs of his wrestling team, alumni support, and more. Kilroe's lifelong connection with his birthplace in Wayne County, Pennsylvania is found throughout the collection, in volumes of historical documents, letters with religious figures from the area, the maintenance of the family farm, cattlebreeding later in life, and more.
The collection holds several volumes of scrapbooks of Kilroe's mother, Sarah, labeled as holding "postcards." In addition to postcards, these often hold greeting cards and other ephemera and memorabilia. Edwin similarly maintained such scrapbooks or accordion folders of cards, ephemera, programs, and the like. Kilroe was a member of a large number of organizations (a list he compiled in 1944, found in box 43, goes on for 12 pages), and the collection includes ephemera, cards, programs, correspondence, etc., related to many of these organizations. These range from political to literary, from religious to legal, from historical societies to athletic, and more. A descendant of Irish immigrants, many documents reflect Kilroe's interest in Irish-American history.
Kilroe's career in the 1910s leading to his appointment as Assistant District Attorney for New York County is documented in a volume of letters and other material (see box 28). His career in the D.A's Office seems to be represented here mostly though scrapbooks and clippings of particular cases, such as the war charities investigation and a so-called "poison pen" matter. His trial on charges of conspiracy not to prosecute a bigamy case is well-documented, as is his resignation in 1924 as Assistant District Attorney.
Kilroe's later career as counsel for 20th Century Fox Film Corporation is only lightly represented. But there is a rich set of scripts, photographs, posters, and publicity material for four of the studio's films of the 1940s: Greenwich Village (featuring Carmen Miranda and Don Ameche), Sweet Rosie O'Grady (featuring Betty Grable and Robert Young), When Irish Eyes Are Smiling, and [Woodrow] Wilson.
The collection has not been processed and the above note and container list is based principally on the labels on the volumes and folders placed by the donor, with some direct observation by the archivist. Container list entries in "quotations" are taken from the labels. The volumes sometimes hold original documents, sometimes photostats, and sometimes a mix; which was present was noted at points by the archivist, but no comprehensive attempt was made to determine and document that here for the entirety of the collection.
Related Materials
New-York Historical has about 125 items associated with Edwin Kilroe, some possibly separated from his overall papers, cataloged individually in Bobcat. Search in Bobcat on "Edwin Kilroe"
Two works by Kilroe concerning Tammany Hall that are held by N-YHS are also available on-line through the Hathi Trust Digital Library: Tammany 1913 and Tammany 1924
Kilroe's large donation to Columbia University of Tammaniana and other documents are cataloged at: Kilroe papers and Tammaniana
The Library of Congress has Kilroe papers concerning his 20th Century Fox years: link to Kilroe
Columbia dorms.; Columbia Literary Monthly.; Columbia Monthly.; Columbia morningside.; Columbia spectator.; Columbian jester.; Bar associations.; Cattle -- Breeding -- Pennsylvania -- Wayne County.; College student newspapers and periodicals.; Criminal investigation -- New York (State) -- New York County.; Irish American Catholics.; Irish Americans -- New York (State) -- New York -- Politics and government.; Irish Americans -- Pennsylvania -- Wayne County.; World War, 1914-1918.; World War, 1939-1945 -- Letters (correspondence); Pennsylvania -- Wayne County -- History.; Ephemera.; Letters (correspondence); Notebooks.; Photographs.; Postcards.; Scrapbooks.; scripts (documents); Theater programs.; Catholic Writers' Guild; Columbia University; New York (State). District Attorney (New York County, N.Y.); Tammany Hall (Political organization); Twentieth Century-Fox Film Corporation; Kilroe (Family)
- Sarah Doherty Kilroe postcards (5 volumes), 1908-1925 (Offsite-box 1)
- Sarah Doherty Kilroe postcards and snapshots (4 volumes); Edwin Kilroe postcards (3 volumes), 1905-1926 (Offsite-box 2)
  Scope and Contents
  The box holds:
  * Sarah Kilroe "postcards, 1908-25" (1 volume), and "snapshots, 1905-26" (3 volumes)
  * Edwin Kilroe "postcards, 1906-20" (3 volumes)
- Sarah Doherty Kilroe postcards, etc. (3 volumes), 1904-1928 (Offsite-box 3)
  * "Postcards, 1926-28" (1 volume)
  * "Receipts and miscellaneous, 1904-17" (1 volume)
  * Condolences re: Sarah's death on December 16, 1928 (1 volume)
- Various (6 volumes), 1918-1940 (Offsite-box 4)
  * Sarah Doherty Kilroe scrapbook of "general/clippings, 1918-28" (1 volume)
  * Edwin Kilroe "snapshots, 1919-26" (1 volume), and "postcards, 1920-29" (2 volumes)
  * "Mary E. Kilroe condolences," died October 3, 1927 (1 volume)
  * "Maude V. Kilroe condolences," died december 23, 1940 (1 volume)
- Cards (2 volumes), 1910-1917, 1939-1944 (Offsite-box 5)
- Cards and scrapbook (2 volumes), 1905-1934 (Offsite-box 6)
  * Scrapbook of "miscellaneous and personal and family, 1905-23" (1 volume)
  * Cards, 1929-34 (1 volume)
- Cards and scrapbook (2 volumes), 1929-1940 (Offsite-box 7)
  * Scrapbook "personal & professional" 1929-40" (1 volume)
  * Cards, 1934-37 (1 volume)
- Various (6 volumes), 1867-1950 (Offsite-box 8)
  * "Kilroe Farms, Tanners Falls, Penn, Deeds to Patrick H. Doherty, 123 acres," 1867, 1872 (1 volume)
  * "Kilroe Farm (pictures, correspondence, news items, advertisements), 1939-50" (this is the first of a two volume set; the second volume is in box 9)
  * "Mansfield family clips, 1890-1942, and McCabe execution clips, 1887" (2 volumes, relates to families in Pennsylvania)
  * Scrapbook "personal & professional, 1938-40" (1 volume)
  * Folder of "reproductions of noted paintings." This holds an assortment of pictorial works, some of artworks, but all generally featuring women, especially of cartoons with sexual innuendo and of other images typically associated with so-called men's magazines, such as Esquire. Similar material is also found in box 46.
- Various (3 volumes), 1921-1950 (Offsite-box 9)
  This box holds:
  * "Kilroe Farm (pictures, correspondence, news items, advertisements), 1939-50" (this is the second of a two volume set; the first volume is in box 8)
  * Scrapbook of "menus, programs, miscellaneous (personal)," 1921-1930s (1 volume)
  * Cards, 1937-39 (1 volume)
- Scrapbooks (3 volumes), 1910-1924, 1936-1940 (Offsite-box 10)
  This box holds 3 scrapbooks of:
  * "Personal & Miscellaneous, 1910-24"
  * "Family & local, 1936-37"
  * "Political poetry, 1936-40"
- Prayer books; Artifacts, 1880s-1920 (Offsite-box 11)
  * Many small prayer books from various family members, including Sarah and Edwin Kilroe, circa 1880s-1920s
  * 2 woodcuts of Edwin Kilroe's bookplates by L.J. Bray, 1905-06
  * Medals, lapel pins, and similar small items, generally related to various organizations. One medal dates from 1920 and reads "The Giants bid you welcome to the Polo Grounds."
- Various (9 volumes), 1867-1944 (Offsite-box 12)
  * Scrapbook of "miscellaneous personal, 1918-26" (1 volume)
  * "Scrapbook of Mrs. Elizabeth Kehoe, 1899-1944" (1 volume, photostats)
  * "Kilroe -- Correspondence 1916-March 1, 1944 re: Origin of the name -- family history," (2 volumes)
  * "The Bennett Farm, Dyberry Township, Wayne County, Pennsylvania," 1940s (1 volume)
  * "Michael Norton (1839-1889)" (2 volumes of photostats re: Norton, a New York politician connected to Tammany Hall). See also box 29.
  * "A History of Ireland," circa 1867 (2 volumes), purchased by Patrick H. Doherty (Sarah Kilroe's father)
- Various (7 volumes), 1899-1944 (Offsite-box 13)
  * Scrapbook re: "Wayne County, Pennsylvania, Society in New York City," 1906-13 (2 volumes)
  * Scrapbook of Mrs. Elizabeth Kehoe, 1899-1944 (1 volume)
  * "Kilroe Farm; Mary Doherty vs. Sarah Kilroe, pleadings, testimony (1913)," (1 volume)
  * "Correspondence: Family genealogy, District Attorney's office, personal, 1919-24" (1 volume)
  * "Horace G. Young prizes -- announcements, papers, etc. 1910-17" (1 volume)
  * Scrapbook,"The Night of the Big Wind in Ireland, January 6, 1839" (1 volume of photostat clippings)
- Correspondence (6 volumes), 1897-1941 (Offsite-box 14)
  * Edwin's "personal correspondence and memoranda, 1897-1941" (4 volumes)
  * "McCarthy -- Doherty -- Kilroe families correspondence, 1898-1919" (2 volumes)
- Various (9 volumes), 1800s-1946 (Offsite-box 15)
  * "Correspondence re: Richard Knight, attorney, December 10, 1940-October 31, 1941" (1 volume)
  * "Commendations (letters, resolutions, editorials), 1904-46" (1 volume)
  * Edwin's lists of "Donations to libraries, 1931-48" (1 volume)
  * "Scrapbook of Sarah Doherty Kilroe," 1800s-1928 (1 volume)
  * "Mary McCarthy -- Patrick H. Doherty family -- history & anecdotes, 1811-1941" (1 volume)
  * Kilroe correspondence. This is a copy of one of the 4 volumes found in box 14.
  * Scrapbook "crime wave" clippings, 1926-28 (1 volume)
  * Listings in city directories of 1814-1938 re: Kilroe family history (1 volume)
  * "Doherty vs. Catskill Cement Co., 1907-18, pleadings, decisions, correspondence" (1 volume)
- Various (6 volumes), 1917-1930s (Offsite-box 16)
  * "Farm items (general)," 1930s (1 volume)
  * "Kilroe Farm. Tanners Fall, Pennsylvania, History of title to the lands, deeds & assignments" (1 volume)
  * "District Attorney's Office clippings, 1917" (2 volumes)
  * "District Attorney's Office correspondence: Mitchell slush fund, war charities frauds, theatre ticket speculation, 1917-19" (1 volume)
  * "Wall Street investigation, 1919-20" (1 volume)
- District Attorney's office clippings (4 volumes), 1917-1920 (Offsite-box 17)
- Various (3 volumes), 1881-1929 (Offsite-box 18)
  * "District Attorney's Office scrapbook, 1921-29 (1 volume)
  * "Bookplates & clippings, 1881-1917" (1 volume)
  * Scrapbook re "general clippings, 1908-1920s" (1 volume)
- "The Kilroe Case" (6 volumes), 1920-1921 (Offsite-box 19)
  This box holds 6 volumes of clippings, correspondence, exhibits, and other documents related to the 1920 indictment of Kilroe on charges that he conspired to not prosecute Napoleon Bourassa on bigamy charges.
- Various (7 volumes), 1901-1930s (Offsite-box 20)
  * "People vs. Kilroe. Printed papers on appeal, 1921" (4 volumes)
  * "Activities of the Almirall Grand Jury, 1919-21" (1 volume)
  * "Kilroe resignation as Assistant District Attorney, December 31, 1923" (1 volume)
  * Scrapbook "legal humor, poetry, 1908-1930s" (1 volume)
- Various (5 volumes), 1909-1924 (Offsite-box 21)
  * Scrapbook re: "legal opinions, letterhead, miscellaneous, 1901-1930s" (1 volume)
  * "Claim of Edwin P. Kilroe against City of New York, 1923-24" (1 volume)
  * "The Matter of EPK (Poison Pen Case), 1924" (1 volume)
  * "People vs. George Maxwell ('Poison Pen' letters, minutes, etc.), 1923" (1 volume)
  * "Monongahela Democratic Club, 19th Assembly District, NY. Campaign literature, forms, circulars, 1909-17" (1 volume)
- "Almirall Grand Jury" clippings (1 volume), 1919-1921 (Offsite-box 22)
- Columbia University publications, 1893-1948 (Offsite-box 23)
  * "The Morningside," Volumes 1-8 dating 1896-1903 (in 5 bound volumes)
  * "Columbia Literary Monthly," Volumes 1-12 dating 1893-1903 (in 7 bound volumes)
  * Bulletin re: residence halls (1911-12)
  * List of student organizations, athletics (1903-04)
  * "History of Columbia College Class of 1920, Senior Year Book"
  * Columbia University club booklet, 1947
  * Columbia football season program, 1948
- Columbia University publications, 1904-1916 (Offsite-box 24)
  * "Columbia Monthly" Volumes 1-7 dating 1904-09 (in 6 bound volumes)
  * "The Dorms" volumes 1-10 dating from 1906-16
  * "Dynamite" 1 issue from March 1916
  * "Challenge" 2 issues from 1916
  The last three bulleted items together in 4 bound volumes.
- Columbia University publications; Kilroe school notes, 1893-1910 (Offsite-box 25)
  * Columbia publication "The Columbian Jester" Volumes 1-8 dating from 1901-08 (in 3 bound volumes)
  * Columbia publication "Alumni News" Volume 1 only dating from 1909-10 (in 1 bound volume)
  * "Notes. Scholastic--Academic. Bookkeeping, Civics, History, Geometry, 1895-96, 1897-98" (1 volume)
  * "Notes. Scholastic. Chemistry. Dwight School, NYC, 1899-1900" (1 volume)
- Kilroe school notes, 1895-1906 (Offsite-box 26)
  * "Notes. Scholastic. Bookkeeping, 1893-94, 1897-98" (1 volume)
  * "Notes. Academic. Literature, Civics, Physics, Chemistry, 1895-96, 1899-1901" (1 volume)
  * "Notes. College. History A & History I, 1900-02" (2 volumes)
  * "Notes. Columbia College. Essays, English, Miscellaneous Notes, History I, 1900-03" (1 volume)
  * "Notes. College-Law. Economics, Diplomacy, Criminal Law, 1903-04" (1 volume)
  * "Notes. Law School. Property, Contracts, Criminal Law, Taxation, 1903-06" (1 volume)
  * "Notes. Law School, 1904-06 (1 volume)
- Scrapbooks (6 volumes), 1907-1920 (Offsite-box 27)
  This box holds 6 scrapbooks:
  * "Programs, souvenirs, menus, 1907-13"
  * "Menus, programs, souvenirs, 1908-18"
  * "Menus, programs, souvenirs, 1918-20"
  * "Menus & correspondence, 1918-24. L.L. [Lora Lieb]." This volume holds memorabilia, etc. from events attended with actress Lora Lieb.
  * "Menus [& programs] C.E.P. [C. Ethel Peckham], 1917-23." This volume holds memorabilia, etc. from events attended with Ethel Peckham. See also box 55.
  * "My First Voyage [to Europe]" and "Execution of the Gun-Man" 1914. Different topics in 1 volume. "Voyage" relates to Kilroe's business trip to England, and the volume includes his summary for context. "Execution" includes clippings related to the execution of Francesco Cirofici (a/k/a "Dago Frank"), which Kilroe attended as a witness.
- Various, 1832-1948 (Offsite-box 28)
  * Scrapbook "My Second Voyage. France and the Battlefields, 1919" (2 volumes). Along with various memorabilia/ephemera, the volumes hold some photographs, especially of post-World War I Verdun.
  * "Pennsylvania Bar (1915); District Attorney's Office (1916)," 1912-16 (2 volumes). Original documents tracing Kilroe's progress at joining the bar and then his early career as Assistant District Attorney under New York County District Attorney Edward Swann.
  * Booklet "Charter of Society of Friendly Sons of St. Patrick in New York" (1832)
  * Booklet "By-laws of St. Patrick's Society of Portland" (1860)
  * 3 books by John H. Dooley, inscribed: "Good living," "Verses concerning the American and Irish Republics," and "Songs of a priest." (1926)
  * Book "God's little acre" by Erskine Caldwell (1934)
  * Book "American armies & battlefields in Europe" (1938)
  * Book "Focus" by Arthur Miller (1945)
  * Book "Raintree County" by Ross Lockridge (1948)
  * Book "The Gilded Hearse" by Charles O. Gorham (1948)
  * Book "Delaware & Hudson Canal History" (1950)
- Various, 1922-1938 (Offsite-box 29)
  * "Michael Norton (1839-1889). Biography, clippings, miscellaneous items, research" (5 volumes, compiled 1938). See also box 12.
  * "Book of the bench and the bar," undated (circa 1913?) with biographies of New York State lawyers and judges, including Kilroe on page 189
  * "References to opinions, January 14, 1907-July 1, 1933." List of opinions rendered in cases Kilroe was involved with in his career as private attorney, in public office and with Fox Film Corporation. Compiled by Kilroe and seems intended as an index to volumes with underlying documents but, if so, those are not in the collection.